(energetic electronic music)
- Hi, everybody.
Welcome to my talk, which
will be about rope simulation
in Uncharted 4 and Last Of Us 2.
My name is Jaroslav Sinecky.
And I'm a programmer at Naughty Dog.
So, this talk has three parts.
The first is like, a general
overview of our rope tech,
how it came to be, what
were the motivations
and the features that we needed.
And then we'll dive into the
technical side of things.
And the second part will be
about a Dynamic Rope Simulation.
And the third part about
Taut Rope Simulation,
which I'll explain in a little
while, what that really is.
So, the rope tech that
you can see in Uncharted 4
and Last Of Us 2, dates back to 2011.
We just shipped Uncharted 3,
and at Naughty Dog after we ship a game
there is usually downtime
of several months
when people are free to
work on their pet projects.
And I had this itch to
write my own solver.
And I looked at ropes in
our previous Uncharted games
and they had lot of limitations,
and Position Based Dynamics
was already very popular
at that time.
So, I thought a rope PBD solver
would be nice little project
for a few weeks, to hone
my simulation skills.
So, yeah.
After a month or two, I
had this rope sim working.
It looked better than Uncharted 3 ropes.
It had some bending stiffness,
and was able to interact with
some simple collision edges,
and with animated character collision.
So, I felt pretty good about it.
And just about then, Kurt Margenau,
a lead designer at the time,
came to my desk and says,
"We'll need some better
rope for Uncharted 4."
So, I finally showed
him my little rope sim.
So, that was pretty rare coincidence.
That doesn't happen often
in a game developer's life,
but I really had no idea
what we were getting into
at that time.
(waves crashing)
- So, Drake was going to have
a grapple hook in Uncharted 4,
and we wanted to set a new bar
for presentation of grapple hook in games.
We wanted something more early-stage
than just a straight line.
We wanted to have an actual bundle of rope
that Drake would have at his belt.
And he would reach for it, and
sling the hook, and throw it,
it would actually wrap around the branch.
We wanted to have slack on
different parts of the rope.
(Drake grunting)
- So, we needed a system
that would be very flexible.
The discretization of the rope
had to be completely dynamic.
We needed to change the
length of the rope on the fly.
And on any frame,
we wanted to be able to
choose any number of points
along the rope and keyframe them.
That way, we could put the
rope into characters' hands
and create these rope coils.
But here, you can see the
keyframe notes on the rope
are yellow, and the white are dynamic.
And in the end,
we settled on the maximum
length for the rope: 14 meters.
So, I could already see
that I was going to
have performance issues.
I'll talk about it little
bit more in the second part
of the presentation.
And we created a system where animators
could keyframe special values
as part of their character animation.
To tell the game what the
character is doing with the rope.
Like, which hand is holding the rope,
or if both, then which goes first?
How much slack should
there be on the rope?
But we didn't just aim for
high bar in presentation.
We wanted to give
players also more freedom
with the grapple hook.
So here you can see, you
have a rope attach point.
And you can drop down on
either side of the rock,
and the rope will just bend
over the edge of the rock.
And then you can swing along the wall,
and the rope will slide
across the rock edges.
And I realize my Dynamic Rope Simulation
is just an utterly unfit
tool for this task.
I was already having problems
with convergence of the rope, sort of,
so, when the rope was close to taut.
And getting it to interact with
a collision in a robust way,
so that we can have gameplay depend on it.
And it just seemed really hard.
So, we needed something different.
(Drake laughing)
- Something like this.
So, here we started with
this straight red line
that connects the hook and Drake's hand.
And then as the hook and Drake move
the line will collide with convex edges,
and wrap around them, and
slide along them, to maintain
the shortest distance between
the end points of the rope.
And this is a completely different thing.
So, this has nothing to do with
the Dynamic Rope Simulation.
I call this Taut Rope Simulation.
And the third part of this
talk will show little bit
how that works.
(Drake grunting)
It didn't seem like a
terribly hard problem to me
at the beginning,
but it turned out I was
quite wrong about that.
(Drake grunting)
So, all the grapple hook
gameplay in Uncharted 4
depends on this Taut Rope Sim.
So, even if the rope has some slack,
we always maintain this
invisible straight line
that connects the attach point,
the hook, and Drake's hands.
And this line has to always
stay out of collision,
and it tells us how far can Drake go.
It also serves as a safe line
for the Dynamic Rope Simulation.
We have these distance
constraints that don't let
the dynamic nodes to get too
far away from the safe line.
And as the rope gets closer to taut,
then the distance gets shorter.
(rope whipping)
And so, for the rest of
Uncharted 4 production,
all the effort on the rope
was focused on getting
this Taut Rope Sim
working and robust enough
so that we could ship the game.
The Dynamic Rope Sim was
really, good as it was,
since it was really just
visual icing on the cake.
- [Drake] Got some big
plans for this winch.
- [Jaroslav Sinecky] So,
another idea designers had
for Uncharted 4 was to put a
winch on our off-road vehicle
to create some new gameplay mechanics.
And they wanted some pretty
long rope for the winch.
So, they were coming to
me from the beginning
and asking for a rope that
would be longer than 14 meters.
I was always saying, "No,
no. 14-meter is the maximum,"
but they really wanted it.
So, they prototyped with
16-meter long winch rope anyway.
Fortunately, the Taut Rope
Sim was a great solution
to this problem also.
The winch rope always has
a lot of tension in it.
So, it was okay to say
it will always be
completely straight line.
No slack at all.
And for the Taut Rope Sim,
the length is not really a limitation.
There's no regular discretization.
So, the cost of the simulation,
really just depends on
the amount and complexity
of the geometry that it
has to interact with.
(wind whistling)
- So, we shipped Uncharted 4.
And then we started
pre-production on Last of Us 2.
And designers were looking
for some new puzzle mechanics.
And they were thinking
Ellie could carry a bundle of rope on her.
And maybe she could just throw
it into the level anywhere
and tie one end somewhere,
and then go around, pick up the other end,
and maybe climb up.
And it seems like we have
this great rope tech,
so we should just be able to do it, right?
And it was actually difficult to explain
why we can't just do it out of the box.
And why is it hard?
The reason is that you
lose the safe line, right?
Once you throw a bundle
of rope into the level,
the Dynamic Rope Simulation
has to take care of itself.
So, it has to behave reasonably,
always stay out of collision
so that Ellie can go and
get it back at any point
and then use it again.
But we decided that it's worth trying.
See if you can pull it off.
At least we limited ourselves to ropes
that are always attached
at some predefined points.
So, you don't just carry it all
but you could throw anywhere in the level.
And for Last of Us 2 production,
all the effort on the rope was focused on
revamping the Dynamic Rope
Simulation for a change.
So, we needed it to make it robust
so it never clips into collision,
and the friction needed a lot of work.
We tried to make it capable
of sliding across collision features even
if you pull on the rope very
fast, or throw it very fast.
And we didn't have any
magic when we didn't want to
have any magic, when bundling the rope,
unlike in Uncharted 4, where
there is no time for that.
So Ellie really meticulously gathers
all the 14 meters of the rope into coils.
We still use the Taut
Rope Sim when we can.
It's there whenever Ellie
is holding the rope,
it tells us how far she can go.
It helps guide the throws.
And as soon as Ellie picks up the rope
we use the Dynamic Rope
as a starting point
to quickly find the invisible Taut Line,
which you can see
happening in the video now.
So, it was a lot of work,
but the rope puzzles
in Last of Us 2 are...
It's a very unique mechanic.
So, you can't really do
anything similar in other games.
And the rope tech was used
for some other elements
in both games.
The weapon straps are
driven by a rope sim.
You can see the enemy weapon strap
has just like, four dynamic
nodes to make it really cheap.
But it's actually enough
for quite believable effect.
It was also for horse reins,
(footsteps padding)
- for dog leashes,
or things like this chained infected.
(chains rattling)
- Okay. So, all these videos we just saw
was to give you some context
for the technical part.
It will come now.
So, we can understand why we did this
and what can be done
with this kind of tech.
And now let's look at
how we actually did it.
Before we start,
I just want to say all the equations
that you will see are here
really just for reference.
So, you don't have to
worry too much about them.
You should be able to follow
the main ideas anyway.
So, the second part is going to be about
the Dynamic Rope Simulation.
And before we get to some
more interesting stuff,
For more details on PBD in general,
I will refer you to this
seminal work by Müller and Co,
but you can find a lot of material
around the web on the topic.
So, let's say we have this piece of rope,
but it's discretized into
a set of connected nodes.
The solid black is fixed
and the others are dynamic.
And in the given moment,
we know the position and
velocity for each of the nodes.
So, this is the current state of the rope.
Now we want to move forward
in time with step ∆t.
So first, we apply some damping,
which will reduce our
velocities little bit.
Next, we apply external forces,
which will modify the velocity some more.
In this case, we have just gravity,
but we could have vit force for example.
And now we use these
velocities to move positions
forward in time by step ∆t.
And this will be the estimate
for our new positions.
But the new positions do not look right.
The rope has stretched.
And also let's assume we
have this purple piece
of collision geometry here,
and the rope is clipping
into the collision.
So now, comes the constraint
solving part of the algorithm.
So, we will need some
constraints to prevent the rope
from stretching and
clipping into collision.
And since this is a
Position Based Dynamic,
the constraints will act on
the position of the nodes
and we will directly move the nodes
to satisfy these constraints.
So firstly, we want a constraint
that keep neighboring nodes
at the same constant
distance l₀ from each other.
And this format looks
slightly complicated,
but what we're doing here really
is very simple and natural.
So, for the first two nodes,
since the first node is fixed,
you just move the second node closer to it
to fix the distance.
And for the second and third node,
since they have a equal masses,
we just move them closer together
by the same distance each.
And then we do the same
for the last two nodes.
And here we add the collision constraints.
Collision constraint.
We just means that we will move the node
out of the collision.
So, we will move it along the plane normal
until it sits on top of the plane.
Now, as you have noticed probably,
by solving one constraint,
we violated the constraints
that we already solved previously.
So, the rope is still
stretched a little bit
at the beginning and
compressed at the end.
So, we will need to go
over these constraints
again and again.
You'll have to iterate
until all the constraints
are more or less satisfied.
And how do we decide that we are satisfied
and we can stop iterating?
So usually, either...
We stop usually when there
is some maximum error
that's smaller than some threshold Ɛ,
or when we reach a maximum
number of iterations.
I can tell you that for PBD,
you don't want to use
the maximum error area
because if you change number of iterations
from frame to frame,
you're basically changing
the stiffness of the solver.
So, you just want to keep the
number of iterations constant.
And after, we found final positions
that satisfy our constraints.
So, we need to find
the correct velocities.
And this is just done by
subtracting from the final position
from the position on the previous frame
and dividing by ∆t.
And now, we have a new
rope state for this frame.
So, that was pretty simple, right?
And the fact that you manipulate
the position of the nodes directly
makes it very easy to
understand what you're doing.
It's also very stable, actually,
because again, as you
control the positions,
the simulation can't really
explode as it easily does
when you're solving for
some internal forces.
But that's why PBD is so popular in games.
So, if you need for
now, limit ourself to...
Or limit our collision geometry
to just a flat ground plane
and the constraint for
that can be expressed
with this simple one line of code.
What I just showed you can be
coded in one, like, afternoon.
And you can get something like this.
So here,
the right end of the rope is
anchored and I let it fall.
Ellie's just standing there for scale.
So, that's not bad, right?
But there are few
problems you will notice.
One is that there is no friction
between the rope and the floor.
And when you look closer
at the rope on the ground,
you can see how it bends
at these sharp angles.
So, the rope has a resistance to bending.
So, we would want to add
some bending stiffness,
or bending constraints to
prevent these sharp angles.
So, how can we create a
bending stiffness constraint?
So, let's say we have these
three neighboring nodes
with masses: m₁, 2, 3.
And we want to straighten
up the segment of rope
by moving them all along
the same direction.
And for now, let's assume
you want to push them
all the way into a straight line.
And how do we find these
unknowns: d₁, d₂, d₃?
So, since the targets are
supposed to be on a straight line,
that gives us one equation.
And then, we need to conserve
the linear and angular
momentum of this little
system of three nodes.
And that gives us two more equations,
Why do I move the nodes in this direction?
All right.
I could move them in
some different direction.
In fact, the most natural here,
would be probably to pivot
m₁, m₃ around m₂ like that
to straighten up this segment.
So, yes.
You do have a lot of freedom
of how to create your constraints.
The bending stiffness could be done
in many different ways.
I just chose this way
because it seemed convenient.
And because I wanted to avoid using
any trigonometric functions
to keep the evaluation
as cheap as possible.
But, the conservation of
momentum is an important rule
that you need to observe.
I know you probably heard
it many times before,
but it's easy to forget.
So, if you ever get the rope
that's resting on its own like a snake,
you probably have a constraint
that doesn't conserve momentum,
and it's adding energy into the rope.
And now we do the math with
the system of equations,
and we get this result
for the displacements.
And each one is a multiplication
of the same expression h.
And because we don't really
want to push the nodes
all the way into the straight
line on each iteration,
it would be way too aggressive.
So, we introduced this multiplier 𝜁
and that will be our bending stiffness.
So, that's the value we
can use to tweak how stiff
should the rope behave
when it comes to bending.
And they respond more loose end to tie.
So, we have coefficient
for bending stiffness,
but the target for the
constraint is still to achieve
a straight line.
So, the constraint will still
be trying to move the rope,
even just a little by a little,
until it reaches a
completely straight line.
The real rope up to a certain point,
you can bend it without
resistance, basically.
It has some free bending radius.
So, if you wan to do
something similar here,
so we introduced this 𝛼f
as a free bending angle
per one meter of rope.
And the equations are here
really just for reference.
But the idea is that simply
the bending stiffness
will only straighten the rope
up to the free bending angle
and then stop acting.
And now we can look at our rope
with this bending stiffness,
bending stiffness constraint added.
And we can see that it does not have
those ugly sharp corners anymore.
It tends to create these
more smooth curves,
but we'll need to do something
about the friction, right?
So, friction is problematic with PBD
because since you're solving
constraints on position level,
you don't know what the
constraint forces are.
So, you don't know what's
the tension of the rope.
You don't know what is
the force between the rope
and the collision.
So, that's one drawback of PBD.
And because, for friction,
you need to know the normal force
between the rope and the collision.
You can't really do that.
But one simple thing that you
can do is just to remember
collision constraint that
were used during the solver.
So, where a node had to be
moved out of the collision
and reduce the tangential
velocity at that node
by some coefficient.
And this is done after the solver,
once you calculated the new
velocities for each node.
And even though this is a
very simple approximation,
it might be all you need.
I'll show you how it looks when we add it
to our little test case.
So, that looks like a pretty
bit of the rope, in this case,
and this is all we needed
for Uncharted 4, for example.
Mostly, because the rope
never had too much slack,
and it was always connected
to something on both ends.
Unfortunately, it wasn't
enough for Last of Us 2.
I'm going to show you these two cases
where it fails to
produce billable results.
So in this first case, the
velocities are reduced,
and just a handful of
nodes that are in contact
with the bar.
That's just not enough to keep
the rope from sliding
back and forth like that.
It is a high contact force
between the rope and the bar
due to the weight of the rope,
which means high friction.
But we don't know that.
And then, there is this other case.
Where the rope just keeps
sliding and sliding.
Yeah. So, for our puzzles it was important
that if it looks like the
rope should stay up there,
that it actually stays up there.
So, we needed to do something
at least a little bit more
realistic for the friction.
And so, one thing we did is this kind of
Static Rope Tension analysis.
This is then, after the solver.
And we look at the rope
shape and nobody touches,
or would upset our collision,
and try to approximate
what the tension, and the
resulting contact force,
and the friction of the rope could be.
And we use facts like, the
tension is zero at the free end
of the rope.
If the rope bends around
the collision edge,
we approximate the resulting
normal force and friction.
If the rope touches collision,
we approximate the normal
force due to the gravity.
If the rope is bending a lot,
and it's not because it
bends around collision edge,
we let the tension fall off to zero.
And for a free hanging segment of rope,
we just add tension
resulting from gravity.
And so, this is all very approximate.
It's completely wrong when
the rope is moving a lot,
because we don't take
velocities into account at all,
but that's okay because the
friction is not important for us
when the rope is moving fast.
So, this worked fine for
us for the rope puzzles,
but there was one more thing we had to do.
So, if you reduce...
If you use friction to reduce velocities
after the solver step,
it is very hard to bring
the rope to complete rest.
Even if you have high
friction and you remove all
the velocity from a node,
if there is some external
force or constraint
pulling on the node,
even just a little bit,
it will move during the next solver step,
because solver doesn't know
anything about the friction.
So, we introduce the friction
constraint into the solver.
It's very simple.
You just need to remember the
original position at the start
of the time step.
So there's the p line
here, and the constraint
is pulling the node back
towards that position.
And we again split the effect
into proportional and constant friction.
And the constant friction
is basically what enables
the effect of static friction.
So if the node is within the radius Sfc
from the original position,
it will snap back to the original position
each time this constraint is processed.
And this coefficient, Sfc, Sfp are just
another empirical coefficient that
you will need to find some
values that work for you.
But they are informed by
the Rope Tension analysis
that I showed you on the previous slide.
And here,
I will just show you that the
friction works much better
in these problematic cases.
Okay.
So, one topic that requires
some more attention
is the convergence,
because it's not a great.
First, if you have a long
rope, a lot of nodes,
that goes around collision
and you pull on it
on one end,
it takes a lot of iterations
to propagate this impulse
to the other end of the rope.
Another good example is the
rope that's almost taut,
like in this little sketch here.
So in this case,
the distance constraints are
pulling the node in direction
that's almost perpendicular
to the direction in
which we want it to move.
So, they are very inefficient.
And from my experience,
you basically need a number of iterations
that's proportional to the
number of nodes in the rope.
But one iteration means going over
all the constraints in the rope.
And that makes the cost of
the simulation quadratic
in terms of the number of nodes.
And it can be very expensive.
So, what can we do to improve that?
One common thing to do is over-relaxation.
So basically, I'm iterating
over each distance constraint.
We will move the nodes
a little bit farther.
Or in other words,
we pretend as if the target
distance is a little bit shorter
than what it really is.
And that helps to reduce
the stretch in the rope
a little bit faster.
And as long as you keep
the relaxation factor ɷ conservative,
it should be still stable.
At least in my experience.
Other common method is multigrid.
So, you create a series of
successively coarser levels
of discretization.
And you start on solving
on the coarsest level.
You run a few iterations.
Go to the next level, et cetera.
And this helps enormously
with the convergence.
Without it, if you have a
rope that's almost taut,
it basically, feels like
it would never converge.
And one note here is that we
had to mark nodes that are
at the collision edge.
And those had to be part
of the coarsest level,
because if you skip them,
the multigrid will start
pulling the rope into collision
and you negate the form, basically.
And then you will have
artifacts in the final results,
where the rope bends in unnatural way.
So, that helped but the rope simulation
was still expensive for the budget we had.
Even have a profile
capture on PS4 of some case
where the rope was really expensive.
And you can see it really sticks out here.
So, just the solver step
is almost 12 milliseconds,
and we only have six cores on PS4.
So, if the rope takes
over one core for like,
half the frame, that's just not good.
So, what do you do when
you run out of ideas
of how we will optimize something?
Yes. You move it to GPU and
it's not the greatest fit.
Because, as I was saying,
rope solving is inherently
very serial process, as
you're propagating impulses
along the rope.
We're on the one wavefront
and process 64 nodes
at the time, but it's not
the same as doing 64 nodes,
one after each other, serially.
So in total,
you end up doing more work on
GPU than you would do on CPU.
This is not the best
utilization of your silicon,
but we still take it.
And this is why.
So here, you have a GPU profile capture,
and it's not much faster.
It takes almost 10 milliseconds
for the compute shader to finish,
but the main difference
and why this is much better
is that it's just one bay front
running on one compute unit.
The PS4 GPU has 18 computing needs.
And if you make sure your
shared resource usage
is not too high, several shaders may share
the same compute unit.
So, you're really just taking
tiny fracture of the GPU.
Saying, you have a
collision plan and you need
to push the node out.
But in real level,
you will have to deal with
some complex geometry,
probably some triangle, triangle mesh,
or maybe just pile of triangles,
or some convex shapes,
but you still do want
to express this geometry
in some simple and compact form.
It can be about it quickly
because you're going to iterate
many times over many nodes.
So, what we did is we tried
to boil down all the geometry
around each node into a
set of collision planes.
And then, we needed to be able
to collide with convex edges.
So, we just marked the pairs of planes
that form a convex edge.
And each node has maximum
of four collision planes
and three convex edges.
So, this sketch here literally represents,
it's like example of
maximum geometry complexity
that could be accurately expressed
with the collision
constraints for one node.
And this second sketch shows the edge one,
when we're looking along the edge.
And it shows what the
collision constraint is doing
for the pair of planes n₁, n₂ .
So we have to...
Since they form convex edge,
we have to check where is
the center of the node.
And if it's in the blue area
A₃, it glides with the edge.
So, we have to push it away from the edge,
otherwise, it collides
with one of the planes.
And this way, the node can
slide smoothly across the edge.
Here we have a debug little from the game
with the node going
through a window corner
with some fairly complex geometry.
And the way this works is
that we first try to estimate
how the node might move during
the upcoming solver step.
Based on its current
velocity, the direction.
Individual neighboring
nodes might be pulling it
based on how much the closest
key frame nodes have moved.
And this gives us A-b-b around the node,
and then we collect all
the geometry in that A-b-b.
And then, we try to be smart
and distill these triangles
into our limited collision constraint set.
So, each triangle gives
us a collision plane.
And then we see if some of these planes
are similar so we can merge them together.
We did the convex edges and
then using current position of
the node,
try to see which planes are
more important than others,
or which ones maybe, we can
ignore completely because they
are behind other planes, et cetera.
Here's just a few examples of simple cases
where this approach breaks down.
So, we only have pairs of
planes scraping a convex edge.
We don't have a concept of group
of convex planes like this,
and it's not trivial to add
this kind of concept into the
solver.
So in this case, if you have a node here,
the plane n₃ will pull
it on the wrong side
of the collision and then n₁ and n₃
starts to fight over the node.
So in this case,
the best thing to do is
just to discard plane n₃,
but it's much harder to do this call.
To make this call.
If the node is somewhere here,
because if it ends up moving to the left,
it will collide with
the plane n₂ like this,
and create what's called
the ghost collision.
And here is another simple example.
So, plane n₁ here doesn't
have any convex edge.
So, it forks as an infinite plane.
And again, it can create a
ghost collision like this.
A lot of effort went into
this heuristics of compiling
complex geometry into
limited set of constraints
for each node and trying to make it work
as robustly as possible.
And it never got totally robust.
Sometimes our geometry is very complex
and the rope needs to
slide across it very fast.
So, this really here was the crux
of the Dynamic Rope Simulation.
Fortunately, in Last of Us 2,
the area where the rope can be
deployed is limited by the
fact that one end of the rope
is always anchored somewhere.
So in the end,
we just had to test these areas properly,
and go and clean up the
show in problematic places.
Also, we have a system that allows us
to take collision triangles
to either ignore rope
or to ignore everything but the rope.
So, we can create special
layer of collision,
of clean collision, just for the rope.
If that's needed for some places.
Shipping a game where you
can do this with a rope,
anywhere in your level
would be much, much harder.
And so, before we finish
the Dynamic Rope part,
I just want to show
you a few useful tricks
you can do with collision constraints.
So, before you send
them off to the solver,
you can look at them, and
see if there is something
suspicious about them
that could cause issues.
Here, we have a node with
two collision planes.
The orange is normal;
indicates the positive side.
So the node is basically
trapped between the planes.
And this would usually happen
when some prop or character
collision would animate
into static collision.
Most often, from Ellie's tie or torso,
and it's important for us to
never let the rope clip into
the static collision.
We don't care that much
about the character capsules.
So, let's say the black
plane is the important one
and the purple, less important.
So, first, we'll project the node out
of the black collision,
This pinching prevention is pretty common
in clothes simulations, I think.
There's another useful trick
you can do during constraint
pre-processing.
I'm going to show you the problem first.
It was mostly affecting weapon
straps because characters
can sometimes animate their
hands through collision.
And if they're handling a
baton that has strap on it,
it can get stuck on a
collision and stretch out.
It could get pretty severe.
I've seen weapons straps
off from enemy weapons
stretched across the
whole level a few times.
Fortunately, there is a
simple trick to prevent that.
Here we have a piece of
rope with four nodes.
The yellow node 0 is key framed.
And we know the length of the rope
between node 0 and 3.
And here we have a collision
constraint for the node 3.
And we can just measure
the distance of this plane
from the keyframed node.
And if it's bigger than
the length of the rope,
then we know this plane
will stretch out the rope,
and we can just ignore this plane.
It's very simple but effective.
Here's the result.
You can see how the
constraints are being removed
as the strap starts to stretch.
Okay.
So now, we will jump
straight into the third part
of this talk, which is going to be about
the Taut Rope Simulation.
And as a reminder, this
video shows what we're after.
So, it's just a line that's
able to collide with collision
and wrap around it, and
slide along the edges
to maintain the shortest
distance between the end points.
The collision needs to
be fully continuous.
So, no matter how fast
the end points of the rope
are moving, or how 10
other collision features,
it never clips through the collision.
And surprisingly, I didn't
find any previous work
on something similar.
So, I'm just going to show
you the approach that we took.
So, we start with this simple case.
We have just a straight line segment A-B.
The game tells us that on the next frame,
the end points A-B have to
move to these new positions.
So, that's our first movement phase.
That's where we want the points to move.
And next, we need to check for collisions.
And we do that by always moving
just one point at a time.
So first, we move point A
and keep the point B fixed.
And during that movement,
this line segment will sweep
this green triangle.
So, we just need to check for
intersection of this triangle
with any neighboring convex edges.
There is no collision here.
So, the point A can move.
And then, the middle is for point B.
And here the triangle intersects
with the blue convex edge.
And the intersection point
is the point of contact.
So we only let the point B move
up until the contact point.
And we enter new edge point
into the rope and we can call it
point C.
And since this collision
face found a contact,
we have to be able to
terminate a collision phase.
And we go back to another movement phase.
And the point B still has
not reached the target point.
So, that will be the new
movement for that point.
And I'm going to move the
camera so that you can hopefully
see better next steps.
So from this angle,
you can see that the rope
is not straightened up,
and we will want to let
the point C slide down
along the collision edge
to straighten up the rope.
Now, how do we find out
how far it should slide?
So here we are, looking
along the edge and rA, rB
are perpendicular distances
of the points from the edge.
And we can rotate point A into the plane
where the edge and the point B are.
And here, we are looking onto the plane.
Here, we can just draw
the straight line between
the point B and A line
to find the intersection
with the edge.
And that's where we want
the point C to move.
And if you go back to the 3D view,
so now, we know how far
we want to let the point C
slide along the edge.
But this was just a movement phase.
So now, we know where we
want points B and C to go,
and we need to go to do
another collision phase
to check if we actually can get there.
And we do it again by
moving points one by one.
So first, we move point C,
and we need to check for
intersection of edges with these
two triangles.
It's all good.
And then we check this
triangle for point B.
No collision here.
And since this collision phase
ended with no new contact
we are done, and this is the
final position of the rope.
So, this is the core of the algorithm.
We are alternating these
movement and collision phases.
Movement phase tells us where
we want points on the rope
to move.
And then, the collision
phase checks for collisions.
And if there is a collision,
we have to go back to another
movement phase to generate new
target positions, et cetera.
And if the collision phase
reports no new contacts,
then we are done.
I'm going to show you one
more example to explain better
the movement phase.
So, here we have a rope that
has two edge points already.
And now the game tells us that
the end points have to move
to these new positions.
And it's not obvious how we
should directly calculate
how far should the two middle points,
B and C move along their edges
to straighten up the rope.
So, we will only use the
first three points A, B, C.
to find out where the point B should move
to straighten up the segment A, B, C.
Then we do the same for the B, C, D.
to the move the point C.
And then, we keep doing that
until we find a position
where the rope is straighten
up or as straight as it can go,
given the collision edges.
So, the movement phase
is an iterative process.
And there's also just one movement phase.
So, as long as each point
on the rope is moving along
the same edge and
doesn't change direction.
You can keep iterating
and they'll be fine.
The target position that
straightens up the rope.
And now we would have to go
back before the collision phase
to actually check if we can get there.
So, there's one problem with
this iterative advancement
of rope edge points.
I'm going to show it on
this piece of geometry.
So now, the upper point
has moved to the right,
and now, we need to slide
all these edge points along
their edges.
But as the edges are getting
closer and closer together.
The iterative method is getting
less and less effective,
until the points pretty much
stop advancing completely.
Fortunately, that is a nice
way to deal with this problem,
since you can basically
unroll it all into 2D,
and solve it in a plane.
So, as you go along the rope,
as long as two consecutive
edges are lying in a plane,
you can keep unrolling
onto the same 2D plane.
So here, we start with edges A and B,
and their plane will be our drawing plane
on the right.
And first, we bring the
point P₀ into this plane
by rotating it around edge A.
And then, since B and C
are parallel to each other,
we can bring edge E into this plane also
by rotating it around edge B.
And then, we do the same for D and E.
And in the end, we also bring
point P₁ into this plane
by rotating it around edge E.
And so, once we have
all this in one plane,
we can just draw a straight
line between P₀ and P₁.
And in 2D, it's easy to
find these intersections.
And then we bring it back into 3D.
As we can see on the left side.
So, only case when you can't
use this trick is when two
consecutive edges on the
rope are askew lines.
In this case, you still need
to use the iterative method.
Okay. So that wasn't that bad.
It gets worse when we
have to start dealing
with intersection of edges.
So here, we have this a
rather ugly piece of geometry,
but it will serve us as a
good showcase to demonstrate
how to deal with edge intersections.
So, our rope has one edge point.
And as the end points are
moving, it slides along
the edge until our
collision phase reports that
we hit some collision at this point.
And here,
the important thing here is
that our collision detection
algorithm has to be able to
report all the edges that come
together at this intersection point.
So, we don't want just the first edge,
or numerically, the first
edge that the rope hits.
We want to be able to gather all the edges
within some tolerance
of the final position.
And this kind of numerical robustness
is important part of the
whole Taut Rope Simulation.
I'll talk about it later a bit more.
Okay. So, we have this point on the rope
that's at intersection
of five different edges.
Now, what should happen next, right?
Should...
What is the point supposed to do?
Should it slide along
some of the other edges,
or should it stay in the intersection?
So, to make it easier to reason about it,
what we do is that we evaluate
all the pairs of two edges.
So, we always only look
at two edges at a time,
and we try to decide
what that intersection
of two edges means.
And then, we put it together at the end.
So, before I can explain that better,
we need to establish some
orientation for the rope.
So, we choose one end of
the rope to be the origin
or the beginning.
And we, we establish the orientation.
That it starts at the origin
and points toward the back.
Toward the end, like that.
And you also need an
orientation for the edges.
So, we'll establish the
orientation like this.
Which basically, means that if
you're standing on the phase
that's facing the, the origin of the rope,
that's the upper phase here,
and you're looking along the
positive direction of the edge,
then the rope has to pass the
edge on the right-hand side.
Okay?
Now, as I was saying, we
will be always evaluating
one pair of edges.
So here, we have two edges: A and B.
And we found a plane in
which, these two edges slide.
And that will be our drawing plane now.
And we orient this plane in
a way that the rope is going
from our side into the plane.
So, I can draw the rope
crossing the plane like this.
And we also have the
orientation of these two edges.
And according to our rule,
the rope has to pass
on the right-hand side
of each of these edges.
So, I know that the rope
has to be somewhere here.
Okay?
On the right-hand side of A,
and the right-hand side of B.
And I drew the of edges
as line that are crossing
each other, but in fact,
they should either start
or end at the intersection.
Otherwise, you will
have, like, a T-junction
in the collision mesh, and
you're not going to worry
about that case.
So, depending on which edge starts or ends
at the intersection, we
will have different cases.
And the first case will be like this.
And in 3D it would usually
look something like this.
So, I call this case Inner
Corner because it's like a corner
where the rope can get caught, basically.
And next thing we do is,
considering where the previous
and next point on the
rope are, we evaluate
in which direction would the
rope slide along each edge,
if we would only have that edge alone.
So, we evaluate it first for edge A
and then we do that for edge B.
And different combinations of
these directions will give us
different sub-cases for the Inner Corner.
So, this sub-case basically
means the rope is trying to move
into the corner, and I call
it Stable Inner Corner.
And that's the case when the
rope stays at the intersection.
And this one,
this sub-case means that the
rope is a abandoning edge B,
and it's moving or sliding along edge A
out of the intersection.
So, I call it Move Along A,
and this would be Move Along B.
And here.
Here, we have this other case.
And in 3D it would look
usually something like this.
So, I call it Unstable Corner.
And depending on which way we would...
Which way would the rope
slide along each edge,
we have this sub-case.
Which, you can basically
choose A or B because the rope
is on the vertex, basically,
and can go either way.
And then, we have a Move
Along A or Move Along B.
And then, we have this case.
Where, if you think about it,
the rope needs to be
on the right side of B,
but the edge A will
not to let it go there.
So, you can basically
disregard the edge B.
In 3D, it would often
look something like this.
So the edge B is basically
coming from the side,
but the rope can't
really interact with it.
I call this case Side Edge.
I had to invent some
names for these cases.
So, I can reason about them
and write a code for them.
And the sub-cases would be
either Ignore B or Ignore A,
in this other case.
Okay.
So, we're not done yet.
So, bear with me for a little
longer through this section.
The rope can cross the
plane of the edges twice.
So, it comes from the origin,
it goes into the plane,
and it comes back again.
Geometrically, since the
rope is at the intersection,
it really just touches the
plane at the intersection point.
But from topological standpoint,
it goes into the plane,
crosses the two edges, and comes back.
And when it comes back,
you'd have to be on the left-hand
side of each of the edges
for the same reason that it had
to be on the right-hand side
when going in.
Um.
So now, let's look at
what segments of the edges
are we dealing with,
because that will give us
different cases again.
So first, let's consider this case.
And maybe this corresponding
3D sketch will make it
more obvious what's going on here.
So basically, the rope was
going over the two edges,
and now it's slid onto the corner.
And it's about to slide off.
Or maybe not, it depends
on the other edges
coming into intersection.
But for now, we're only
thinking about these two edges.
I call this case Outer Corner.
And the sub-cases are either
the rope goes over A and then B,
or first over B and then A.
And finally, this last case,
or this one.
Those are the actual cases, basically.
And in theory, it will
be something like this.
So, the edges would have to be
like, relatively sharp edges
so that the rope can
go over them like that.
And depending on which way the rope
wants to slide along each edge,
we have these sub-cases,
which are equivalent to
what you already saw before.
So, we have a Stable Inner Corner,
or Inner Corner Move
Along A, and Move Along B,
or we can have also, Unstable Corner.
Okay.
So now, equipped with all these
topological categorization,
we can look at our test case.
So, we have these five
intersecting edges here,
and we'll call them A, B, C, D, E.
And we found out with what
their orientations are.
And then, we have already
the topological case
for each pair of the two edges.
And we'll get, we'll get
this kind of metrics here.
And first, we look for
some Side Edge cases,
and we see that B and E are Side Edges.
So, we can ignore these edges.
And now we only have A, C, D left.
And we see that there is an Inner Corner,
Stable Inner Corner between A-C and A-D.
And if there is any Stable Inner Corner,
it means that the rope
is caught in the corner
and stays there.
So, we just keep the rope
point at the intersection.
But the end points of the
rope will keep moving now.
So, they move just a little bit,
but the situation has changed slightly.
So we have new metrics here.
The edges E and B switched orientation,
but they are still Side Edges.
So, we can still ignore them.
And it is no more Stable Inner Corner.
So, the rope should move out now.
And instead, we have
Inner Corner Move Along C,
and Inner Corner Move Along D.
So we know we will abandon edge A.
And then also, edges C and D
create an Outer Corner C-D.
So, we will want to split the
rope point into two points.
First, will go along edge C.
And second, will go along edge D.
So, here it goes.
And then, we can go back
and it would be basically
the same thing but in reverse.
So, at certain point, the two,
the two rope points will
get within some tolerance
from each other, and we will
merge them into one point.
And then, we will reach the intersection,
spend a while in the Stable Inner Corner,
and then, Move Along A out of the corner.
But even just for this
case of each intersection,
the situation can change
dramatically depending on what
the end points of the rope are doing.
So just for illustration,
if rope ends go like this,
then suddenly, edges A
and B are now forming
an Outer Corner.
And then, you can do this,
which is pretty common.
Where the rope basically lies
within the face of a triangle.
And then, when it reaches a
edge, it's parallel to the edge.
So, we need to be able to
deal with these cases also.
So, maybe this is a good moment
to address this numerical
robustness I mentioned before.
So when you do any kind
of distance tests, like,
is the rope touching an edge
or two edges intersecting,
you can't just test for some
distance being zero, right?
You need to use some tolerance
and you want to be consistent
with this tolerance.
It has to go through the whole algorithm
and becomes part of all
the collision tests,
all the distance, or intersection tests.
And we used tolerance of 0.001 millimeter,
which is quite large, a necessity
for just numerical errors
But that way, it also
covers geometric errors.
If you, for example,
have two boxes and you place
them next to each other
in your, in your level
builder or level editor.
It may be that when, when this
geometry comes into the game,
the vertices that were aligning it,
are not exactly at the
same coordinates, right?
And you don't want your rope
to slip into the tiny slot
between the boxes.
And another problem is there
are some tests or predicates
in this algorithm that are very important,
but it can become a numerically unstable.
With example is the actual orientation.
It's important to get it right.
Otherwise you basically tell
the rope to go on the wrong
side of the, of the edge.
But sometimes, like in
this case we just saw,
when the rope is close
to parallel to an edge.
There is no good way to tell
what the orientation should be.
So, it's just important to tread carefully
when writing these
predicates, and think about
what happens in the singular cases,
and what are the consequences.
There is no time to go
into the more details,
but I just thought I should bring it up
because it definitely brings
another level of difficulty
to the problem.
And speaking of difficulties.
So, the Taut Rope Simulation,
also never got 100% robust.
To be able to deal with any
geometry that you throw at it.
Here are the main reasons why.
So, it's the numerical robust bugs there
that I just mentioned.
It's pretty hard to get that 200%
in an algorithm that's fairly complex.
The edge intersections
prove to be hard too.
So, the topological
classification that I showed you,
where we always just look
at one pair of edges,
and then we also test in
which direction the rope
wants to slide by only looking at, looking
at one edge in isolation.
So, it mostly works,
but I did find some obscure
cases where there was some more
intricate interdependency
between the edges
at an intersection.
At certain angle of the
rope going through it,
and the algorithm would just
make the wrong decision.
and we didn't have time and
the real need to dig deeper
into all these cases.
And one limitation, coming
just from code design,
is that we only support maximum
of eight edges per rope point.
So, if you have a very
taxing error collision mesh
with lot of convex edges coming together,
and the rope needs to
slide over that vertex,
it will just randomly
drop some of the edges.
There is all this in this case,
usually not catastrophic,
since we have already
a lot of edges, and it will
keep the rope more or less
on the surface.
So, I'm going to show you
this scene from Uncharted 4.
Drake wraps the winch
rope around the tree,
as many times before,
and now he's going to
drive up the mudslide.
- [Drake] We're all set.
Here we go.
(mechanical whirring)
- Easy.
- [Sully] Uh-oh!
- [Drake] Whoa, whoa, whoa!
(car crashing)
(boulders smashing)
- Don't panic! Don't panic!
- [Jaroslav Sinecky] So, did
you notice just what the rope
was doing as the Jeep slid off?
Of course you didn't.
It's pretty much
impossible to see anything
because it happens very fast,
and there is a lot of particles.
And the camera is not even
looking in that direction.
Nevertheless,
this was probably the hardest
case for the Taut Rope
in the whole game.
The reason it was hard is
because the rope is sliding
very fast across lot of geometry.
And since it's going mostly
parallel to the surface,
it's colliding with all these
edges at very sharp angles
and basically, hitting
all these edge cases
and numerically unstable tests.
And we could have failed
this particular case,
as literally, nobody will be
seeing what the rope is doing.
But it was kind of nice this
case and easy to reproduce.
Here is a little more detail
and it goes step-by-step.
And...
So, if you pay attention
to this place here.
Yeah.
So, right now you can
see that the rope clipped
into the collision, but it will recover.
It will get pulled out again.
And then there is another
problematic spot later.
I think somewhere here.
So, this is just to
show that not everything
was a total success,
but it also shows the general
tendency in these cases
is that even if something
goes wrong locally,
usually the other edges
with hold the rope up
and pull it out of collision eventually.
So, it rarely has a
catastrophic consequences
for the gameplay.
Fortunately.
Okay. So, let's wrap it up.
So, when Last of Us 2 came out,
somebody noticed the
rope, and there was this
long thread on Twitter
with also, reactions
from game developers.
And a lot of them saying that
seeing these was actually
stressing them out and
giving them nightmares.
Some people expressing their
fear that their producers
will now ask for the same thing.
So this talk, hopefully,
if somebody actually tries
to implement something similar,
will give him some pointers and help avoid
some of the pitfalls that we went through.
But also, I'm hoping this can
help make a better judgment
of how difficult it is, and
if it's worth the effort.
It can maybe serve as a
defense when some game director
asks you for a rope like Last of Us 2.
Because, yes, it wasn't easy.
Over eight years in development.
And even though the rope,
definitely wasn't the
only thing I was doing
during those years.
It was by far, I would say, the hardest.
But your mileage vary.
You might not need everything we did.
If you only need some visual
elements: hanging ropes,
or vines, or weapon straps.
Some simple rope PBD solver
is actually very easy
to put together, as I showed.
Now, depends if you need
the rope to be long,
with a lot of nodes, because
then, maybe you will have to
deal with convergence
and performance problems.
How realistic you need the friction to be?
How complex is the geometry?
Because that's big one because
that hugely impacts how hard
will the problem be.
And not surprisingly,
if you have game play
depending on your rope sim,
that's when things get hard.
So for the Taut Rope,
which drove all the
gameplay in Uncharted 4,
and the Dynamic Rope,
which we needed for
gameplay in Last of Us 2,
proved to be hard problems.
What I showed you for
the Taut Rope Sim may not
seem very complicated,
but it is a lot of code,
a lot of complicated bookkeeping,
and dealing with edge cases,
and numerical robustness.
So, don't underestimate that
part, because I sure did.
And as I already intimated,
even though significant effort
went into these systems,
you never got them 100%
robust to be able to deal
with just any geometry.
So again,
the geometric complexity
is the biggest factor here.
So if you can limit, in any way,
how complex is the geometry that the rope
has to interact with.
That's, that's the biggest
help you can give to yourself.
You know, by limiting
the area where the rope
can be deployed, or what
kind of collision features
it needs to interact with.
Maybe, getting some clean
and simple collision authored
for these areas, or have some
offline pre-processing step
to clean it up.
So, all these things,
it's definitely worth looking into.
(tense dramatic music)
- And one last piece of advice.
So, if you're going to
implement something like that,
it will not be easy.
So, it's worth to invest
some time into creating
some solid debugging tools
to make your life easier.
One nice thing about the
rope simulation like that
is that it's a relatively
isolatable piece of software.
So, can grab a piece of
a DPDK memory and use it
as a ring buffer, and store all your input
and state for each frame.
And then, if something goes wrong,
you can pause, and step back,
and look at what failed.
You bring up all your diagnostic drawing,
and when stepping forward,
you can run exactly the same simulation.
Our engine is not
deterministic. Not even close.
But the rope simulation is.
There is nothing that would
be breaking determinism here.
So, you can find a frame
when something went wrong,
and then just play that
frame over and over,
and debug it as you, as you want.
We even created a Rope
Dump where if somebody,
mostly testers, would
find something went wrong.
They could just dump the ring buffer,
plus some collision
shape data into a file.
And then, I could load
it up on my Dev Kit,
and debug it as I wanted.
And so, this tool was absolutely crucial.
You could never ship a game
with these rope features
without the rope debugger.
And that's the end of my talk.
So presumably, I'm literally
answering your questions
in the chat right now,
but you can also contact me at this email
if you have more questions,
or ideas, or comments.
So, thank you for listening.
(energetic electronic music)